Mss.SMs.Coll.4
American Philosophical Society
Walter C. Shields Photograph album
Bulk, 1911-1913
1911-1928
Mss.SMs.Coll.4
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Volume(s) 18.6 x 28.8 cm. album, 208 photographs
Walter C. Shields was the Superintendent of Schools of the Northwest district of the Alaska division for the Bureau of Education of the United States Department of the Interior from 1910-1918. The photograph album reflects the dual role the Bureau of Education played in providing schools for Inupiat Eskimo children and domestic reindeer herding for their parents. The 199 original black and white photographs, dated 1911-1913, reflect individual and group portraits of Inupiat Eskimos, interior and exterior views of their homes and schools, reindeer sleds and round-ups. Taken by Shields and his colleague H. Barnette, some specific locations include Barrow, Wainwright, Noatak, Selawik, Buckland, Candle, Deering, Wales, and Shishmaref. Nine other photographs, dated 1916, 1928, are of dwellings and dog sleds in the White Mountains.
Shields, Walter C.
Background note
Walter C. Shields was the Superintendent of Schools of the Northwest district of the Alaska division for the Bureau of Education of the United States Department of the Interior from 1910-1918. The photograph album reflects the dual role the Bureau of Education played in providing schools for Inupiat Eskimo children and domestic reindeer herding for their parents. In 1884, the federal government had determined that the natives in Alaska were largely self-sufficient so the government role would be restricted to educational needs. In 1890, Sheldon Jackson, a Presbyterian missionary and head of the United States Bureau of Education in Alaska recruited missionaries who would serve as teachers for Wales, Point Hope and Barrow. Several church missions had an official connection with the bureau by which their missionaries were employed as teachers of the federal school system. Two years later, Jackson launched a program for developing reindeer herds to sustain the Inupiat Eskimos. Reindeer were entrusted to these mission schools with teacher’s general supervision of herds and herders. With the gold rushes of Klondike and Nome, the Congress doubled the sums allotted for the bureau schools in the early 1900s. The population explosion of these two cities caused a new demand for products produced by the reindeer. In the midst of these changes, Walter C. Shields began his tenure as Northwest division superintendent. In a twofold capacity, he oversaw the increase in schools and reindeer herding in the Seward Peninsula. In his efforts, he tried to protect the natives from corruption by non-natives while encouraging their wealth and prestige by means of reindeer herding. Some of his contributions consist of creating new settlements or reviving older ones with new placements of schools. He introduced reindeer fairs where herd owners could exchange information, listen to lectures on animal husbandry, and band together in reindeer associations. The fairs were very popular among the Eskimos who respected Shield’s innovations. Unfortunately, his untimely death during the 1918 flu epidemic ended his work.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: The photographs in the album reflect Shield’s visit from 1911-1913 to the many new and re-established areas of school locations in arctic Northwest Alaska. The 199 original black and white silver gelatin ethnological photographs of Inupiat Eskimos include: group shots outside and inside of schools, individual portraits in winter dress, family living conditions in igloos, dog sleds, and reindeer round-ups. Taken by Shields and his colleague H. Barnette, primarily along the Chukchi sea coast, some specific locations include Barrow, Wainwright, Kivalina, Kotzebue, Buckland, Deering, Shishmaref, Wales, Teller, and Golowin, with some inland sites at Kobuk, and Noatak. The prints, affixed to black paper leaves of a leather-bound album, contain white ink captions with dates. Nine other photographs, dated 1916, 1928, are of dwellings and dog sleds in the White Mountains.
References
Flanders, Nicholas E. Missionaries and professional infidels: religion and government in western Alaska. Arctic anthropology, v.28, no.2, 1991. 572.05 Ar25 Murdoch, John. Ethnological results of the Point Barrow expedition. Ninth annual report of the Bureau of Ethnology…1887-88. (Washington: Government Printing office, 1892) 572.061 Sm6 v.9 Sheldon, Jackson. Annual report on introduction of domestic reindeer into Alaska … (Washington: Government Printing office) 328.73 Un3b 6th (1896); 636 J13 (1894, 1899)
Provenance
Purchased February, 2008
Related Archival Materials note
The APS has several rich photographic collections documenting Native Americans, including the A. Zeno Shindler American Indian Photograph Collection, the Frank Speck Photograph Collection.
Arctic peoples--Pictorial works; Eskimos--Alaska--Education; Eskimos--Alaska--Missions; Gelatin silver prints; Indians of North America--Alaska; Indians of North America--Alaska--Seward Peninsula; Indians of North America--Alaska--Social life and customs; Inupiat--Alaska--Barrow; Inupiat--Alaska--Kotzebue; Inupiat--Alaska--Seward Peninsula; Inupiat--Alaska--Social life and customs; Inupiat--Alaska--Teller; Inupiat--Alaska--Wales; North Slope Borough (Alaska); Northwest Arctic Borough (Alaska); Northwest Coast Indians; Reindeer--Arctic regions; Seward Peninsula (Alaska)
- School house, Selawik, 9 January 1912
- Inupiat dwellings, Selawik, 9 January 1912
- Mission hospital, Kotzebue, 25 January 1912
- Trail between Selawik and the Kobuk, adlers along a creek, January 1913
- Trail between Selawik and the Kobuk, the lonesome pine, January 1913
- School house, Shungnak, January 1913
- New Teacher's residence, Shungnak, January 1913
- Inupiat, group with dog, Barrow, March 1913
- Inupiat group, dwelling, Barrow, March 1913
- Inupiat at tea, Barrow, March 1913
- Tukpuk, portrait, Barrow, March 1913
- Trail from Council to Candle, fixing a sled, 17 December 1911
- Trail from Council to Candle, Simon having lunch, 17 December 1911
- Leaving Council herd, group, 16 December 1911
- Shungnak herders, group, 4 January 1912
- Inupiat school children, Buckland, December 1913
- Inupiat school children, group, Buckland, December 1913
- Christmas tree and presents, Selawik, December 1913
- Inupiat igloo, Selawik, December 1913
- Inupiat students, building, Kivalina, March 1913
- Inupiat oldest, youngest students, Kivalina, March 1913
- Officers school republic, Kivalina, March 1913
- Earl Woodrow Wilson Negewanna, portrait, Kivalina, March 1913
- Klemetsen and wife, with deer, Kivalina, March 1913
- Reindeer, named Link, Kivalina, March 1913
- Saw Tooth Mountains, Mosquito Pass, man, reindeer, sled, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, Mosquito Pass, man sitting on sled, April 1912
- Head of reindeer, no. 1, 1912-1913
- Head and shoulders of reindeer, no. 1, 1912-1913
- Mrs. Hefler, reindeer, harness, sled, 1912-1913
- Head and shoulders of reindeer, no.2, 1912-1913
- Reindeer, 1912-1913
- Deering to Igloo: Inupiat reindeer herders, 1913
- Deering to Igloo: Inupiat man with sled, 1913
- Deering to Igloo: reindeer fighting with feet, 1913
- Deering to Igloo: reindeer fighting with horns, 1913
- Driving sled through deep snow, 1913
- Leaving Kivalina, group, 1912-1913
- Leaving Barrow herd, group, 1912-1913
- Leaving Council herd, group, 1912-1913
- Alaskan camp site, Walter C. Shields, 1913
- Camp in mountains, 1913
- Chester Sevick, Jimmie Orealuk, 1913
- Saw Tooth Mountains: reindeer, sled, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains: reindeer, sled, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, landscape, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, landscape, April 1912
- Selawik to Kobuk: reindeer driven by Walter C. Shields, 1912-1913
- Selawik to Kobuk: reindeer, new harness, 1912-1913
- Deering to Igloo: reindeer sled, Walter C. Shields, 1913
- Deering to Igloo: reindeer sled, Walter C. Shields, 1913
- Saw Tooth Mountains, landscape, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, sled, April 1912
- Reindeer camp near Mosquito Pass, 1912-1913
- Dwelling at Shishmaref, 1912-1913
- Reindeer used from Kivalina to Ice Cape, 1912-1913
- Reindeer used from Kivalina to Ice Cape, with sled, 1912-1913
- Reindeer race at Teller, 1912-1913
- Reindeer race at Teller, action photograph, 1912-1913
- Reindeer race at Teller, Mr. Lopp, 1912-1913
- Shishmaref to Wales: fast reindeer, 1912-1913
- Shishmaref to Wales: strong reindeer, 1912-1913
- Deering herders, group, 1 February 1912
- Noatak herders, group, 7 January 1912
- School house, Noatak, 17 January 1912
- School children, parents, outside school house, Noatak, 17 January 1912
- Reindeer, Kobuk herd, 1912-1913
- Northern entrance to Mosquito Pass, 1912-1913
- Walter C. Shields, portrait, native attire, 1912-1913
- Walter C. Shields, portrait, native attire, 1912-1913
- Walter C. Shields, full-length portrait, native attire, 1912-1913
- Roofs of Inupiat dwellings, Shishmaref, 25 April 1912
- Mr. and Mrs. Hefler, residence, Shishmaref, 25 April 1912
- Seal blubber, Shishmaref, 25 April 1912
- School, residence, Shishmaref, 25 April 1912
- Inupiat children, group, St. Lawrence Island, 12 July 1912
- Inspecting the meat herd, Nome, January 1912
- Inspecting the meat herd, Nome, January 1912
- Dwelling of modern type, Selawik, December 1913
- Overseers, Quaker Church, Decdmber 1913
- Inupiat family, dwelling, interior, 1912-1913
- Kugruk River between Selawik and Kobuk, 1912-1913
- Residence, school, Shungnak, January 1913
- Judge Moran’s fox ranch, January 1913
- C.D. Jones, Jimmie, Shungnak, 1913
- Camp between Noatak and Kivalina, 1913
- Camp on Humboldt Creek, near Deering, 1913
- Reindeer and dogs travel together, 1913
- Camp, cooking, 1912-1913
- Camp, sleeping, 1912-1913
- Camp, Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Camp, Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Ship “Transit” at Teller, 9 July 1912
- Dr. Neumann, Mr. Starr, King Island, 8 July 1912
- Mungnok’s camp, Kotzebue Sound, January 1913
- Sleds, Kotzebue Sound, January 1913
- Tuliksek and wife, Cape Krusenstern, January 1913
- Tuliksek’s dwelling, Cape Krusenstern, January 1913
- Walter C. Shields, reindeer named Gasolene, Sinuk, April 1913
- Walter C. Shields, reindeer named Uncle Sam, Sinuk, April 1913
- Camp, Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Camp, alcohol stove, Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Camp, tent, Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Reindeer round-up, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, run-way, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, last herd, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, Golovin, 10 December, 1911
- Reindeer round-up, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Mr. and Mrs. Cox, Miss MacLeod, Kotzebue, 25 January 1912
- School children, group, Kotzebue, 25 January 1912
- Minungun’s reindeer camp, Kotzebue, 13 January 1912
- Minungun, with other Inupiat, in tent, Kotzebue, 13 January 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Saw Tooth Mountains, April 1912
- Reindeer camp, Golovin mission, 9 December 1911
- Reindeer men at round-up, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Driving the herd in from the tundra, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Herd in the woods, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Dr. Barbour at river bank, Noatak, January 1918
- Church house, Noatuk, January 1918
- Sleds on ice, seal hunt, Noatak, January 1918
- Sleds on ice, seal hunt, Noatak, January 1918
- Cape Thompson, natural arch, 1918
- Cape Thompson, strata, 1918
- Inupiat couple, Icy Cape, 1918
- Sampson, trapper, Noatak, 1918
- Mr. and Mrs. Cram, Alice Ahlook, Barrow, March 1913
- Inupiats with Mr. and Mrs. Cram, Barrow, March 1913
- Inupiat school group, Barrow, March 1913
- Dog sled team, Barrow, March 1913
- Inupiat dwellings, King Island, 8 July 1912
- Inupiat dwellings, roofs, King Island, 8 July 1912
- Inupiat dwelling, Bering Sea, King Island, 8 July 1912
- Old man of the island, King Island, 8 July 1912
- Mr. Harnden and family, Noatak, 17 January 1912
- Inupiat group, Noatak, 17 January 1912
- School house, Kivalina, 21 January 1912
- School house, Kivalina, 21 January 1912
- Mr. Bates, cache with bear skin, Wainwright, March 1913
- Inupiat school children, Wainwright, March 1913
- Mr. and Mrs. Bates with Inupiat group, Wainwright, March 1913
- Inupiat school group, two teachers, Deering, 30 January 1912
- Inupiat village group, Deering, 30 January 1912
- Missionary Mrs. Gooden with Inupiat child, Deering, 30 January 1912
- Mrs. Hare, Inupiat interpreter, Deering, 30 January 1912
- Mrs. Hare, Miss Hunnicutt, Deering, 30 January 1912
- Jack and Ashagak in dwelling, Deering, 30 Jan. 1912
- Reindeer round-up, reading ear mark, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, milling, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Reindeer round-up, corral, Golovin, 10 December 1911
- Walter C. Shields, Council, 12-16 December 1911
- Fish River, Council, 12-16 December 1911
- Willuk’s cabin, reindeer camp, Council, 12-16 December 1911
- Tautuk, chief herder, group, Council, 15 December 1911
- Mr. Snow with Inupiat group, 15 December 1911
- Dr. Watkins, Dr. Neumann, Mrs. Caldwell, Wales, 10 July 1912
- Caches, Wales, 10 July 1912
- Dr. Neumann, reindeer camp, St. Lawrence Island, 12 July 1912
- Dr. Neumann with Inupiat group, 12 July 1912
- Bluffs with reindeer sled between Wales and Teller, 3 May 1912
- Lost River between Wales and Teller, 3 May 1912
- Walter C. Shields, Jimmie, camp below Kivalina, 1912-1913
- Inupiat camp dwelling, below Kivalina, 1912-1913
- Mr. and Miss Bates, Inupiat school children, Kivalina, 21 January 1912
- Inupiat school children, school house, Kivalina, 21 January 1912
- Inupiat dwelling at Kivalina, 21 January 1912
- Camp Humbold creek en route Deering to Igloo, 1912-1913
- Modern Inupiat dwellings, Wales, 1 May 1912
- Older Inupiat dwellings, Wales, 1 May 1912
- Five Inupiat girls, outside, Kivalina, March 1913
- Inupiat girl sitting on oil tank, Kivalina, March 1913
- Walter C. Shields, Inupiat group, Kivalina, March 1913
- Walter C. Shields, Inupiat group, camp, Kivalina, March 1913
- Inupiat group at reindeer herd, Kivalina, March 1913
- Walter C. Shields, Inupiat couple, Kivalina, March 1913
- Mrs. Maguire, two Inupiat women, Kivalina, March 1913
- Inupiat mother, child carried on back, Kivalina, March 1913
- Maguire’s son, Inupiat children, Kivalina, March 1913
- Walter C. Shields, Mr. Maguire, Kivalina, March 1913
- Tarlak, head council man, Kivalina, March 1913
- Assukhanna, Inupiat man, Kivalina, March 1913
- Inupiat dwelling, Buckland, 1913
- Inupiat dwelling, Shungnak, 1913
- Inupiat dwelling, Kotzebue, 25 January 1912
- Snow cache, Kotzebue, 25 January 1912
- Inupiat school children, Kotzebue, 25 January 1912
- Inupiat village group, Kotzebue, 25 January 1912
- Inupiat dwelling, Mr. Evans’ dwelling, above Pitmagea, 1913
- Inupiat dwelling, boat frame, Pitmagea, 1913
- Inupiat dwelling, Icy Cape herd, 1912-1913
- Inupiat dwelling, skylight of walrus skin, 1912-1913
- Inupiat school children, uniforms, Wainwright, 1912-1913
- Coal ship, winter quarters, 1912-1913
- Barrow mission, March 1913
- Reindeer Company haul poles for corral, near Shungnak
- Inupiat dwellings, Shungnak, n.d.
- White Mountain, September 1916
- Barrow, August 1916
- Dr. Ronold, sled, dogs, Kanakauak, 1928